Finding Aid for Allan L. Dreyfuss papers, 1948-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Allan L. Dreyfuss papers 1948-1991
Dreyfuss, Allan L., 1919-2011.
4.5 linear feet
2011059 Aa 2
Foreign correspondent for Stars and Stripes and Reuters stationed in Germany after World War II, speech-writer for New York mayor Robert F. Wagner and for executives of the Ford Motor Company, member of the Public Affairs staff of the New Detroit Committee; articles and speeches written, various topical files from his work with Ford and New Detroit; and miscellaneous news articles from his years as correspondent for Reuters.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Dreyfuss’s daughter AE Dreyfuss and family members, Peter, Stephen, Jonathan, Sam, Madeleine, Nathaniel, and Noah (donor no. 10529 ). The collection came to the library in April 2011.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Allan Dreyfuss was born July 21, 1919 in Brookline, Mass. He received his A.B. in Literature and Humanities from the University of Chicago in 1941. He had begun graduate study leading to a Ph.D. degree when he enlisted in the Army Air Corps and was assigned to serve as correspondent to Stars and Stripes (1942-1946). After the war he covered the Nuremberg trails for Stars and Stripes and other news services. Dreyfuss remained in Europe serving as West Germany and Berlin correspondent and Chief of Bureau for Reuters News Agency (1946-1949), Central European and Germany correspondent for the Reporter Magazine (1949); and West Germany correspondent for ABC (1949-1950).
In 1950, Dreyfuss also served as unit publicity director for 20th Century-Fox on the production of Anatole Litvak production of "Decision before Dawn." From 1951 to 1952, he was correspondent in Germany for The Times of London. He then became bureau chief for Radio Free Europe in Stockholm and in 1953, he moved to Paris as director of the Radio Free Europe Paris Bureau. He served for six and one-half years. He then returned to the United States, and after a brief hiatus he went to work for Current Magazine as associate editor and foreign editor. In 1962, he joined the staff of Robert Wagner where he wrote the bulk of the New York Mayor's speeches.
In 1963, he joined the Ford Motor Company beginning with editorial specials first in the Public Relations Department, later in the International Public Relations Division. At Ford, Dreyfuss held a variety of editorial and speech-writing responsibilities for Henry Ford II and other top executives. In 1967, while on loan from Ford, Dreyfuss began working on the Public Affairs staff of the New Detroit Committee. NDC was an organization of business and civic leaders established after the Detroit Riots of 1967 to find solutions to issues of employment, housing, and other kinds of discrimination that had led to the disturbance. With others, Dreyfuss wrote the weekly New Detroit report which summarized the group's activities. Dreyfuss also acted in the role of NDC's historian.
Dreyfuss retired from Ford in 1991 but kept busy writing plays, many winning awards. He died in 2011.
The Allan Dreyfuss collection has been arranged into the following series: Career (prior to 1963); Articles / Speeches written; New Detroit Committee; Ford Motor Company; and Political. Although there is some documentation of Dreyfuss's career as a foreign correspondent stationed mainly in Germany following World War II and as a publicity director for 20th Century-Fox, the bulk of the papers relate to his work after 1963 when he came to work with the Ford Motor Company as a speech writer for the company's top executives: Henry Ford II, Alex Trotman, Donald Petersen, H. A. Poling among others. These men trusted Dreyfuss with the Ford message, especially when they traveled abroad and the notes and comments he received about the speeches reflect that trust. No doubt for this reason, Henry Ford II allowed Dreyfuss to work with New Detroit as historian and note-taker at the meetings of the organization's executive committee.
Subjects:
Dreyfuss, Allan L., 1919-2011.; Ford, Henry, 1901-1988.; Petersen, Donald E.; Poling, H. A.; Trotman, Alex J.; Wagner, Robert F. (Robert Ferdinand), 1910-1991.; Ford Motor Company.; New Detroit, Inc. (Detroit, Mich.); Reuters Ltd.; Automobile industry and trade.; Foreign correspondents--United States.; Speech writers.; Detroit (Mich.)--Race relations.
- Career (prior to 1963)
  - Biographical and personal (Box 1)
  - These 21 (Box 1)
    (booklet of profiles of the main 21 Nazi defendants at the Nuremberg trials, first published in Stars and Stripes, and compiled as a booklet by Stars and Stripes; reprinted 60 years later with a foreword by Dreyfuss)
  - Reuters articles circa 1946-1948, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Reporter Magazine, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Lurton Blassingame (literary agent) 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Articles relating to Criminal Investigation Division (CID) 1950 (Box 1)
    (perhaps written for Reporter)
  - Germany materials (miscellaneous) 1950 (Box 1)
  - Twentieth-Century Fox
    - Script for "Legion of the Damned" (later renamed "Decision before Dawn") (Box 1)
    - Press releases and other materials relating to "Legion of the Damned" (Box 1)
  - The Times: correspondence and other materials, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Radio Free Europe, letters, notes, clippings, and miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Articles / Speeches
  - Manuscripts of articles written on speculation (Box 1)
  - Sherwin Williams Paint (article written for US Information Agency) (Box 1)
  - Speeches of NY Mayor Robert F. Wagner (many of them written by Allan Dreyfuss) January-November 1962, 11 folders (Box 1)
    (also include scattered earlier speeches of Wagner)
- New Detroit Committee
  - "Aide Memoire" -- Notes and comments of AD on the meetings of the NDC 1967 (scattered 1968 1969) (Box 2)
  - Agenda book 1968 (Box 2)
  - New Detroit Task Force Projects -- Financial projection summaries March 1968 (Box 2)
  - New Detroit Committee weekly reports 1967-1968
    - Final (Box 2)
    - Drafts (Box 2)
  - New Detroit Committee press releases, speeches and related material (Box 2)
  - Manuscripts of New Detroit Committee writings (Box 2)
  - Drafts of New Detroit Committee writings, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Various New Detroit Committee memoranda (Box 2)
  - New Detroit Committee dramatic skits (Box 2)
  - Community groups: include CORE, Ad hoc action group, Students for White Community Action, People Against Racism (Box 2)
  - Printed Material (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Ford Motor Company
  - Correspondence and memoranda 1965-1968 (Box 3)
  - Speeches written for company executives
    - Henry Ford II 1969, 1976-1983 (Box 3)
    - Donald Petersen 1977-1986, 1988 (Box 3)
    - H.A. Poling 1984-1987, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Alex J. Trotman 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - L. Lindsey Halstead 1984-1987 (Box 3)
      (Halstead was Vice President, Asia-Pacific and Latin American Automotive Operations)
    - Allan D. Gilmour 1986, 1991 (Box 3)
      (Gilmour was Executive Vice President and Chief Financial Officer)
    - Various Ford speakers 1964, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Various Ford speakers 1980-1982, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Speeches on occasion of Ford retirements (Box 4)
    - Working files 1987-1990, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Outlines, notes, and related (Box 4)
  - Topical files
    - Special Report: "The Urban Crisis and Ford Management; A special report of members of Ford Motor Company Corporate Community Relations Committee" March 12, 1968 (Box 5)
    - Foreign-owned multi-national corporations operating in the United States (collected material and notes) 1972 (Box 5)
    - Arab boycott of the Ford Motor Company 1986, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - McInally Memorial Lecture: "The Business of Education" (outline) (Box 5)
    - Draft: "What's Source for the Thunderbird; The Public Affairs Implications of Global Outsourcing; A Ford Perspective" 1985 (Box 5)
    - Research study: "Auto scrappage and Disposal" 1970, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Henry Ford II trip to Far East June 1978 (Box 5)
    - Employment evaluations / Performance appraisal of Allan Dreyfuss 1986-1990 (Box 5)
    - Allan Dreyfuss notes from his retirement at Ford October 1991 (Box 5)
    - Ford and personal miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Political
  - Notes of meeting of Dissident Democrats January 1968 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Conference of Concerned Democrats 1967-1968 (Box 5)